<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Ponti, Daniel J.</origin>
        <origin>Rosa, Carla M.</origin>
        <origin>Blair, James Luke</origin>
        <pubdate>2019</pubdate>
        <title>Table of field observations of fault rupture and ground deformation features following the Mw 6.0 South Napa Earthquake of August 24, 2014</title>
        <geoform>Tab-delimited text file</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Menlo Park, CA</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/F7P26W84</onlink>
        <lworkcit>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Ponti, Daniel J.</origin>
            <origin>Rosa, Carla M.</origin>
            <origin>Blair, James Luke</origin>
            <pubdate>2019</pubdate>
            <title>Digital datasets documenting fault rupture and ground deformation features produced by the Mw 6.0 South Napa Earthquake of August 24, 2014</title>
            <geoform>Data Release</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Menlo Park, CA</pubplace>
              <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>https://doi.org/10.5066/F7P26W84</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </lworkcit>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>This product is the result of a comprehensive compilation of site-specific field descriptions and displacement measurements where tectonic faulting and ground failure produced visible deformation that fractured and disturbed the ground surface. The resultant data is distributed as a tab-delimited text file. All post-earthquake ground rupture observations and slip/displacement measurements are those in the public domain, including data that have been published in summary reports elsewhere.</abstract>
      <purpose>Data was collected and compiled in order to improve our understanding the nature of the West Napa Fault System and its seismic hazard potential.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20140824</begdate>
          <enddate>20141112</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-122.3948268</westbc>
        <eastbc>-122.2774628</eastbc>
        <northbc>38.35552715</northbc>
        <southbc>38.12670252</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
        <themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
        <themekey>earthquake occurrences</themekey>
        <themekey>field inventory and monitoring</themekey>
        <themekey>faulting (geologic)</themekey>
        <themekey>deformation (geologic)</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>USGS Metadata Identifier</themekt>
        <themekey>USGS:5c1a392de4b0708288c2e9a5</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>Geographic Names Information System (GNIS)</placekt>
        <placekey>California</placekey>
        <placekey>San Francisco Bay</placekey>
        <placekey>Napa County</placekey>
        <placekey>Napa</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>none</accconst>
    <useconst>none</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Daniel J Ponti</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. GEOLOGICAL SURVEY, PACIFIC REGION: EARTHQUAKE SCIENCE CENTER</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Scientist Emeritus</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Mail Stop 977, 345 Middlefield Road</address>
          <city>Menlo Park</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>94025</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>650-329-5679</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>dponti@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>U.S. Geological Survey - Benjamin A. Brooks, Emma Crewdson, Coyn Criley, Stephen B. DeLong, Suzanne Hecker, Thomas L. Holzer, Kenneth W. Hudnut, James J. Lienkaemper, Alexandra J. Pickering, Daniel J. Ponti, Carol S. Prentice, Carla M. Rosa, David P. Schwartz, Robert R. Sickler, John C. Tinsley III. California Geological Survey – Clif Davenport, Timothy E. Dawson, Marc P. Delattre, Wayne Haydon, Jeremy Lancaster, Maxime Mareschal, Cynthia Pridmore, Ron S. Rubin, Gordon G. Seitz, Mark O. Wiegers, Chris Wills. Others – Cooper Brossy (Fugro), Michael Buga (Fugro), Don Hoirup (California Department of Water Resources), Chris Hitchcock (Infraterra), Keith Kelson (U.S. Army Corps of Engineers), Andy Lutz (Infraterra), Alex Morelan (University of California, Davis), Jared Pratt (Rgh Consultants), Kevin Ryan (Ryan Geological Consulting), Heidi Stenner (unaffiliated), David Trench (Fugro), Chad Trexler (University of California, Davis), Donald Wells (AMEC), John Wesling (Office of Mine Reclamation), Dana Zaccone (unaffiliated)</datacred>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Ponti, Daniel J.</origin>
        <origin>Rosa, Carla M.</origin>
        <origin>Blair, James Luke</origin>
        <pubdate>2019</pubdate>
        <title>The Mw 6.0 South Napa Earthquake of August 24, 2014—Observations of surface faulting and ground deformation, with recommendations for improving post-earthquake field investigations</title>
        <serinfo>
          <sername>Open-File Report</sername>
          <issue>2019-1018</issue>
        </serinfo>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Menlo Park, CA</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>https://doi.org/10.3133/ofr20191018</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted</logic>
    <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>We commonly noticed location discrepancies on the order of 10 m, when comparing different observations at collocated sites, or when comparing reported coordinates to their “true” locations derived from high-resolution orthoimagery. In several cases, we noticed location discrepancies of more than several hundred meters. The largest errors appear to have been associated with incorrectly reported datums or where observations were recorded either with the GPS turned off or before the receiver acquired a positional lock. For observations reported on a fault trace that was visible on post-earthquake lidar, InSAR, or orthoimagery, we adjusted the observation locations to align with fault traces mapped on the imagery, by using observer descriptions, photographs, and Google Maps Street View to constrain the adjustment. These adjusted stations are likely accurate to within a few meters, relative to the base imagery, and in most cases accurate to less than 1 m where there is sufficient documentation from ground photographs. For stations with insufficient documentation to inform any adjustment to the original, reported location, the original coordinates are maintained and the positional uncertainties of those stations are therefore unknown, but most likely on the order of 10 m.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Observations of ground deformation from the South Napa earthquake were documented at different levels of detail, which required standardization and reconciliation among different source datasets. Overall, all information received from site observations fell into one or more of these categories: a) waypoints.—point data attributed only as to the presence or absence of faulting or ground deformation; b) GPS track logs.—points along traverses showing areas; canvassed on the ground; c) text descriptions.—descriptions of ground rupture referenced to a locality; d) digital photographs—photographs of ground rupture features, with or without embedded coordinate information or other camera metadata; e) measurements.—fault slip and fracture offset data; information may be tabulated into a spreadsheet or other type of table, or recorded in a text description. Text descriptions and measurements were then combined by the originators into a standard data schema. Each record in the Observations table constitutes a station, which is a location where an observation (text description, photograph, and [or] measurement) was made by a single investigator or a field team working together (an observer) during a single visit on a specific date. If the same observer revisits the same locality on a different day or time and records a separate observation, this constitutes a separate station in the Observations table. Minimum data recorded for a station in the Observations table are name(s) of the observer(s); observation date; locality coordinates, and at least one of the following: (1) text describing the character of ground deformation, (2) measurement of slip or indication of displacement sense, or (3) one or more photographs. 

In addition to recording information directly reported by field investigators, the Observations table contains several attributes that were derived during compilation; these include a classification of the type of feature or material affected by ground deformation and the interpreted origin of deformation inferred directly from the observation itself or from context, based on location and information from nearby stations.</procdesc>
        <procdate>2018</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Point</direct>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>0.0197558934</latres>
        <longres>0.0250376172</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D_WGS_1984</horizdn>
        <ellips>WGS_1984</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Observations Table</enttypl>
        <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>stnid</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Identifier for the observation station. A station is assigned where descriptions, displacement measurements and (or) photographs have been obtained at a site at a given date and time by an observer or group of observers working together. Repeat observations at different times by the same observer or group of observers are assigned different stnids.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1</rdommin>
            <rdommax>1341</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>intid</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Internal identifier. Used to link an observation record to associated records in the Photos table.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>1</rdommin>
            <rdommax>9969</rdommax>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>citation</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>If the data or photographs from this observation are published elsewhere, the original publication is cited here.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Textual description of the data's original publication.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>obs_date</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Date of the observation as year, numerical month, and day of month.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>A textual description of the date as numeric values of the year, month and day, each separated by colon (for example, 2014:09:03 represents September 3, 2014).</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>latitude</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Latitude coordinate of the station in decimal degrees, WGS84 datum. These values are derived either from the coordinate provided directly by the observer, or are digitized during compilation using airborne imagery and ground photographs to more accurately locate the station on the feature of interest. Observations of fault features were typically relocated to coincide with mapped fault locations as derived from high-resolution imagery, lidar data or InSAR data.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-90</rdommin>
            <rdommax>90</rdommax>
            <attrunit>angular distance in degrees, negative values represent south latitude</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>longitude</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Longitude coordinate of the station in decimal degrees, WGS84 datum. These values are derived either from the coordinate provided directly by the observer, or are digitized during compilation using airborne imagery and ground photographs to more accurately locate the station on the feature of interest. Observations of fault features were typically relocated to coincide with mapped fault locations as derived from high-resolution imagery, lidar data or InSAR data.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-180</rdommin>
            <rdommax>180</rdommax>
            <attrunit>angular distance in degrees, negative values represent west longitude</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>orig_lat</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Original latitude reported by the observer in decimal degrees, WGS84 datum.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-90</rdommin>
            <rdommax>90</rdommax>
            <attrunit>angular distance in degrees, negative values represent south latitude</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>orig_lon</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Original longitude reported by the observer in decimal degrees, WGS84 datum.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <rdom>
            <rdommin>-180</rdommin>
            <rdommax>180</rdommax>
            <attrunit>angular distance in degrees, negative values represent west longitude</attrunit>
          </rdom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>photo</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Indicates if photographs are associated with this station</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Y</edomv>
            <edomvd>Yes</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>N</edomv>
            <edomvd>No</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>observer</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Last name of the observer or observers who provided the information/photographs. Full names and affiliations are listed in the data set credit of this metadata record. A single name may be listed where observations may have been collected by a group of individuals working together.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Textual string of the observer or observer(s) last name(s). Multiple names separated by "/"</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>observed_feature</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The type of feature where fault offset is observed or the type of materials that are offset or disturbed.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Curb/Sidewalk</edomv>
            <edomvd>Offset or damage to sidewalks and curbs located adjacent to roadways and constructed of concrete, although a small number of curbs may be of asphalt construction. This classification also includes concrete patios and pathways.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Foundation</edomv>
            <edomvd>Offset or damage noted in concrete, brick/masonry, or wood perimeter foundations of structures.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Pavement</edomv>
            <edomvd>Offset or damage to paved roadway and runway surfaces, dominantly made of bituminous asphalt or concrete. Includes gravel shoulders adjacent to paved roadways.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Soil</edomv>
            <edomvd>Offset or fractures in soil and shallow fill. Includes compacted soil (such as dirt roads or trails) and gravel or mixed gravel/dirt roadways.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Vineyard Row</edomv>
            <edomvd>Offset noted of a row or rows of grape vines and (or) stakes.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Wall/Fence</edomv>
            <edomvd>Offset or disturbance noted in a vertical wall or fence constructed of wood, concrete or masonry.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Other</edomv>
            <edomvd>Damage or offset from ground deformation to miscellaneous features not otherwise classified. Includes such features as decking, swimming pool shells, and railroad rails and ties.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>description</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Notes and descriptive information provided by the observer, if applicable. Descriptions are edited to correct typographical and grammatical errors, and to remove irrelevant or personal information, such as property owner names and addresses, and so on.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>A textual description of the feature observed.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>fault_azimuth</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Strike of the fault zone in degrees from true north (0–360). If qualified by a double asterisk (**), the fault azimuth is estimated by the compilers from the rupture map and used for slip calculations.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>A textual description of the fault azimuth, in degrees from north (0-360), plus any qualifiers, such as **</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ss_displacement</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Strike-slip displacement, the length of the horizontal component of total slip on the fault plane, in centimeters. If qualified by an asterisk (*) the value is reported as an approximation or represents some undocumented component of horizontal fault movement, such as separation normal to a faulted feature or piercing point separation. If qualified by a double asterisk (**), strike-slip component is computed by the compilers using a fault azimuth value estimated from the map.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>A textual description of the strike-slip displacement, as a numerical value in centimeters, plus any qualifiers, such as **, *, &lt;, ~, etc.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ss_sense</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Sense of strike-slip displacement, either reported or computed from slip vector information and fault azimuth.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>RL</edomv>
            <edomvd>right-lateral displacement.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>LL</edomv>
            <edomvd>left-lateral displacement.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>ext_offset</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The amount of horizontal opening (extension) measured normal to the fault plane, in centimeters. If qualified by an asterisk (*), value is an estimate. If qualified by a double asterisk (**), extension is computed by the compilers using a fault azimuth value estimated from the map.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>A textual description of the extension, as a numerical value in centimeters, plus any qualifiers, such as **, *, &lt;, ~, etc.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>comp_offset</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The amount of horizontal shortening (compression) measured normal to the fault plane, in centimeters. If qualified by an asterisk (*), value is an approximation.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>A textual description of the shortening, as a numerical value in centimeters, plus any qualifiers, such as *.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>vert_offset</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>The vertical component of dip-slip displacement, in centimeters. If qualified by an asterisk (*), value is an approximation.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>A textual description of the vertical offset, as a numerical value in centimeters, plus any qualifiers, such as *.</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>upthrown_side</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>If a vertical component of fault displacement is reported, this is the cardinal direction of the upthrown side.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>N</edomv>
            <edomvd>north side up</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>E</edomv>
            <edomvd>east side up</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>S</edomv>
            <edomvd>south side up</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>W</edomv>
            <edomvd>west side up</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>trace</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Identifies the fault trace (A-G) or region (H-U) where the observation is located.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>A</edomv>
            <edomvd>Fault trace A</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>B</edomv>
            <edomvd>Fault trace B</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>C</edomv>
            <edomvd>Fault trace C</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>D</edomv>
            <edomvd>Fault trace D</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>E</edomv>
            <edomvd>Fault trace E</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>F</edomv>
            <edomvd>Fault trace F</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>G</edomv>
            <edomvd>Fault trace G</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>H</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region H (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>I</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region I (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>J</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region J (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>K</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region K (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>L</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region L (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>M</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region M (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>N</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region N (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>O</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region O (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>P</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region P (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Q</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region Q (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>R</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region R (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>S</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region S (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>T</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region T (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>U</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region U (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>V</edomv>
            <edomvd>Region V (location shown in Fig. 13 of the cross-referenced publication listed in the metadata record).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>origin</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Interpreted cause of the ground deformation observed at the station, either inferred directly from the observation or from context based on fracture orientation, displacement sense, setting or nearby observations.</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Lateral spread</edomv>
            <edomvd>Surface cracks inferred to have been produced by lateral movement of a soil mass toward a free face, likely owing to shaking-induced liquefaction or shear failure of subsurface materials.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Shaking</edomv>
            <edomvd>Ground deformation inferred to have been produced solely by shaking-induced settlement or slope failure (for example, slumps, soil falls, bank failures).</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Tectonic</edomv>
            <edomvd>Ground deformation observed along a linear trend with a displacement sense consistent with the earthquake source mechanism. Right-lateral offsets may be observed directly or inferred from a pattern of left-stepping en echelon surface fractures. Tectonic surface rupture includes seismogenic rupture that has propagated to the surface from the earthquake source and slip resulting from shallow strain release triggered by shaking or changes in near-surface stresses from the earthquake</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
        <attrdomv>
          <edom>
            <edomv>Uncertain</edomv>
            <edomvd>Fractures with orientations and displacement sense not consistent with the earthquake source mechanism, or isolated observations of ground deformation with no discernible lateral displacement. Features of uncertain origin that are associated with InSAR lineaments may in fact be from faulting where displacements are small, distributed, or overprinted by shaking-related settlement or pavement decoupling, or to shallow, secondary faulting that results from folding, distributed shearing and surface block rotations along these trends. Alternatively, these linear zones may simply reflect stratigraphic or structural boundaries controlling deep-seated gravity failures (for example, block glides and ridge-spread phenomena) or that separate different geologic materials that have settled differentially owing to shaking. Sites of ground deformation not associated with linear trends and that cannot otherwise be readily explained by typical earthquake-induced ground failure mechanisms (for example, liquefaction or shallow slope failure), are also included in this classification.</edomvd>
            <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
          </edom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>U.S. Geological Survey – ScienceBase</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey – ScienceBase</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <state>CO</state>
          <postal>80225</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>sciencebase@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>Distributor assumes no liability for misuse of data.</distliab>
    <techpreq>The Observations table is distributed as a tab-delimited text file with Windows line delimiters (CRLF). The file can be readily imported into spreadsheet or database applications. The table can also be imported into GIS applications to produce a point feature class, using the latitude and longitude attributes to define the point geometry.</techpreq>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20200818</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntper>Daniel J Ponti</cntper>
          <cntorg>U.S. GEOLOGICAL SURVEY, PACIFIC REGION: EARTHQUAKE SCIENCE CENTER</cntorg>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>Scientist Emeritus</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>Mail Stop 977, 345 Middlefield Road</address>
          <city>Menlo Park</city>
          <state>CA</state>
          <postal>94025</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>650-329-5679</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>dponti@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
